[
    {
        "Question":"** Resting membrane potential of skeletal muscles maintained mainly by which ion of the following?",
        "Option 1":"Na",
        "Option 2":"K",
        "Option 3":"Ca",
        "Option 4":"Cl",
        "Option 5":"Mg",
        "Correct Answer":"K"
    },
    {
        "Question":"What is the type of ion transport through Na\/K pump in the cell membrane?",
        "Option 1":"Simple diffusion",
        "Option 2":"Facilitated diffusion",
        "Option 3":"Primary active transport",
        "Option 4":"Secondary active transport",
        "Option 5":"Osmosis",
        "Correct Answer":"Primary active transport"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** A 40 year old patient develops autonomic dysfunction after brain injury. Which of the central nervous system parts is important for regulation of autonomic nervous system?",
        "Option 1":"Pituitary gland",
        "Option 2":"Hypothalamus",
        "Option 3":"Pineal body",
        "Option 4":"Globus pallidus",
        "Option 5":"Thalamus",
        "Correct Answer":"Hypothalamus"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which of the following will be affected by damage of dorsal root ganglia?",
        "Option 1":"Sensation",
        "Option 2":"Motor",
        "Option 3":"Parasympathetic",
        "Option 4":"Sympathetic",
        "Option 5":"Somatic motor",
        "Correct Answer":"Sensation"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 60 year old woman with apical lung tumor develops manifestations of Horner syndrome. Whis is due to damage to which of the following?",
        "Option 1":"Anterior horn cell of spinal cord",
        "Option 2":"Dorsal motor neucleus of vagus",
        "Option 3":"Edinger wistiphal neucleus",
        "Option 4":"Lateral horn cell of spinal cord",
        "Option 5":"Posterior horn cell of spinal cord",
        "Correct Answer":"Lateral horn cell of spinal cord"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which of the following is preganglionic neurotransmitter in the nervous system?",
        "Option 1":"Acetyl choline",
        "Option 2":"Noradrenaline",
        "Option 3":"Adrenaline",
        "Option 4":"Dopamine",
        "Option 5":"Doputamine",
        "Correct Answer":"Acetyl choline"
    },
    {
        "Question":"What is the neurotransmitter secreted by greater splanchnic nerve inside the adrenal medulla to stimulate it for secretion of catecholamine?",
        "Option 1":"Acetylcholine",
        "Option 2":"Noradrenaline",
        "Option 3":"Adrenaline",
        "Option 4":"Dopamine",
        "Option 5":"Histamine",
        "Correct Answer":"Acetylcholine"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** Young male is very anxious and has tachycardia about his upcoming operation. What is the physiology happened to him?",
        "Option 1":"Adrenaline released from adrenal medulla",
        "Option 2":"Noradrenaline released from adrenal medulla",
        "Option 3":"Adrenaline released from sympathetic system",
        "Option 4":"Noradrenaline released from sympathetic system",
        "Option 5":"Increased amount of circulating noradrenaline",
        "Correct Answer":"Noradrenaline released from sympathetic system"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Patient in anxiety, there some physiological changes in his body as releasing adrenaline, from which adrenaline are secreted?",
        "Option 1":"Adrenal cortex",
        "Option 2":"Adrenal medulla",
        "Option 3":"Presynaptic sympathetic ganglia",
        "Option 4":"Sympathetic nerve ending",
        "Option 5":"Parasympathetic nerve ending",
        "Correct Answer":"Adrenal medulla"
    },
    {
        "Question":"18 year old man after he ate canned food, he felt weakness all over the body and diagnosed having flaccid paralysis due to botulinum toxin, in which neurotransmitter does this toxin act on?",
        "Option 1":"Acetylcholine",
        "Option 2":"Adrenaline",
        "Option 3":"GABA",
        "Option 4":"Glutamate",
        "Option 5":"Serotonin",
        "Correct Answer":"Acetylcholine"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 70 year old man with history of insulin controlled diabetes and having myasthenia gravis is admitted to hospital with a 12 hour history of a painful white leg. A femoral artery embolus is shown on angiography. Regarding myasthenia gravis, which receptor may be affected?",
        "Option 1":"Presynaptic adrenergic receptor",
        "Option 2":"Presynaptic acetylcholine receptor",
        "Option 3":"Postsynaptic adrenergic receptor",
        "Option 4":"Postsynaptic nicotinic cholinergic receptors",
        "Option 5":"Postsynaptic muscarinic cholinergic receptors",
        "Correct Answer":"Postsynaptic nicotinic cholinergic receptors"
    },
    {
        "Question":"45 year old presented by flaccid paralysis and diagnosed as botulinum toxicity, what is the mechanism of action of this neurotoxin?",
        "Option 1":"Block muscarinic cholinergic receptors at postsynaptic neuron",
        "Option 2":"Block nicotinic cholinergic receptors at postsynaptic neuron",
        "Option 3":"Block release of acetylcholine from the presynaptic neuron",
        "Option 4":"Block lateral horn cell",
        "Option 5":"Block anterior horn cell",
        "Correct Answer":"Block release of acetylcholine from the presynaptic neuron"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** Which one of these does not change its size during skeletal muscle contraction?",
        "Option 1":"A band",
        "Option 2":"I band",
        "Option 3":"H band",
        "Option 4":"Sarcomere",
        "Option 5":"Myofibril",
        "Correct Answer":"A band"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A patient presented with ptosis, fatiguability and weakness all over body, physician suspected he has myasthenia gravis, which of the following site of tumors can cause myasthenia like symptoms?",
        "Option 1":"Thymus",
        "Option 2":"Adrenals",
        "Option 3":"Lung",
        "Option 4":"Liver",
        "Option 5":"Kidney",
        "Correct Answer":"Thymus"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which of the following is indication of activity of sympathetic nervous system in an anxious patient before surgery?",
        "Option 1":"Bronchodilatation",
        "Option 2":"Micturition",
        "Option 3":"Miosis",
        "Option 4":"Increased peristalsis",
        "Option 5":"Hypoglycemia",
        "Correct Answer":"Bronchodilatation"
    },
    {
        "Question":"What is the sign of unopposed parasympathetic stimulation?",
        "Option 1":"Mydryasis",
        "Option 2":"Urine retention",
        "Option 3":"Broncodilatation",
        "Option 4":"Detrusor muscle contratction",
        "Option 5":"Constipation",
        "Correct Answer":"Detrusor muscle contratction"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which of the following resulted from parasympathetic nervous system activity?",
        "Option 1":"Pupil dilatation",
        "Option 2":"Diminished blood flow to skeletal muscle",
        "Option 3":"Increase peristalsis",
        "Option 4":"Decrease gastric emptying",
        "Option 5":"Ejaculation",
        "Correct Answer":"Increase peristalsis"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 22 year old man has gun shot in his back in the lumber region. He has increased tone and hyperreflexia of his right leg but he cannot feel his left leg. What is mostly diagnosis?",
        "Option 1":"Tabes dorsalis",
        "Option 2":"Subacute degeneration of the cord",
        "Option 3":"Brown sequerd syndrome",
        "Option 4":"Syringomyelia",
        "Option 5":"Herpes zoster",
        "Correct Answer":"Brown sequerd syndrome"
    },
    {
        "Question":"30 year old man has a gunshot to her back, which transect the cord at left side presents with features suggestive of brown Sequard syndrome, the clinical findings will include which of the following?",
        "Option 1":"Left sided weakness, left sided proprioception and vibration loss, right sided loss of pain and temperature",
        "Option 2":"right sided weakness, right sided proprioception and vibration loss, left sided loss of pain and temperature",
        "Option 3":"right sided weakness, right sided proprioception and vibration loss, right sided loss of pain and temperature",
        "Option 4":"right sided weakness, right sided proprioception and vibration loss, right sided loss of pain and temperature",
        "Option 5":"left sided weakness, right sided proprioception and vibration loss, left sided loss of pain and temperature",
        "Correct Answer":"Left sided weakness, left sided proprioception and vibration loss, right sided loss of pain and temperature"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 68 year old man presents to the plastics team with severe burns to his hands. He is not distressed by the burns. He has bilateral charcot joints. On examination, there is loss of pain and temperature sensation of the upper limbs. What is mostly the diagnosis?",
        "Option 1":"Transverse myelitis",
        "Option 2":"Subacute degeneration of the cord",
        "Option 3":"Brown sequerd syndrome",
        "Option 4":"Syringomyelia",
        "Option 5":"Epidural hematoma",
        "Correct Answer":"Syringomyelia"
    },
    {
        "Question":"55 year old suffered from spasticity and exaggerated extensor tendon reflex, what is the site of lesion causing those manifestations?",
        "Option 1":"Lower motor neuron lesion",
        "Option 2":"Basal ganglion lesion",
        "Option 3":"Corticospinal tract lesion",
        "Option 4":"Cerebellar lesion",
        "Option 5":"Posterior horn affection",
        "Correct Answer":"Corticospinal tract lesion"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** 45 year old man prepared for lumber disc operation. After surgery on his back, he has lost cold and hot sensation on his lower limb, which spinal track may be affected?",
        "Option 1":"Dorsal column",
        "Option 2":"Corticospinal tract",
        "Option 3":"Cerellospinal tract",
        "Option 4":"Lateral spinothalamic tract",
        "Option 5":"Ventral spinothalamic tract",
        "Correct Answer":"Lateral spinothalamic tract"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 55 year old suffered from unsteady gait and dysmetria during movement, what is mainly the site of the lesion?",
        "Option 1":"Basal ganglia",
        "Option 2":"Anterior horn spinal cord",
        "Option 3":"Posterior horn spinal cord",
        "Option 4":"Cerebellum",
        "Option 5":"Cerebral cortex",
        "Correct Answer":"Cerebellum"
    },
    {
        "Question":"55 year old man after RTA suffered form muscle flaccidity and areflexia in some muscle of his upper limb. Which lesion may be the cause of those symptoms?",
        "Option 1":"Corticospinal tract lesion",
        "Option 2":"Lower motor neuron lesion",
        "Option 3":"Basal ganglia lesion",
        "Option 4":"Cerebellar lesion",
        "Option 5":"Posterior horn affection",
        "Correct Answer":"Lower motor neuron lesion"
    },
    {
        "Question":"34 years old man weight lifter presented by back pain and affection spinal tracts and diagnosed having central cord syndrome. What are the manifestations may be appears that disease?",
        "Option 1":"Loss of pain and temperature bilateral",
        "Option 2":"Loss of pain and temperature on one side",
        "Option 3":"Loss of fine and proprioception bilateral",
        "Option 4":"Loss of fine and proprioception on one side",
        "Option 5":"Early paralysis on both sides",
        "Correct Answer":"Loss of pain and temperature bilateral"
    },
    {
        "Question":"59 year old come presented to emergency room after spinal cord trauma. On examination, the physician said that he has spasticity and hyperreflexia in his limb, what is the site of lesion causing those manifestations?",
        "Option 1":"Corticospinal tract lesion",
        "Option 2":"Lower motor neuron lesion",
        "Option 3":"Cerebellar lesion",
        "Option 4":"Basal ganglia lesion",
        "Option 5":"Hypothalmus lesion",
        "Correct Answer":"Corticospinal tract lesion"
    },
    {
        "Question":"35 year old male presented to neurological outpatient clinic by back pain and weakness of lower limbs and diagnosed as central disc prolapse with lower motor neuron lesion manifestation. What is mostly diagnosis?",
        "Option 1":"Syringomyelia",
        "Option 2":"Cauda equina",
        "Option 3":"Brown Sequard syndrome",
        "Option 4":"Posterior cord syndrome",
        "Option 5":"Central cord syndrome",
        "Correct Answer":"Cauda equina"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** 34 year old man presented after RTA with complete transection of spinal cord but still have urinary bladder control. What is the cause of this control?",
        "Option 1":"Intact pelvic splanchnic nerves",
        "Option 2":"Intact parasympathetic to external urethral sphincter",
        "Option 3":"Intact innervation to external sphincter",
        "Option 4":"Intact sympathy innervation to external sphincter",
        "Option 5":"Intact pudendal nerve",
        "Correct Answer":"Intact pelvic splanchnic nerves"
    },
    {
        "Question":"60 year old man with history of playing boxing when he is young presented to outpatient clinic with cog wheel rigidity and resting tremors. What is the site of lesion causing those manifestations?",
        "Option 1":"Basal ganglia",
        "Option 2":"Anterior horn spinal cord",
        "Option 3":"Post horn spinal cord",
        "Option 4":"Cerebellum",
        "Option 5":"Cerebral cortex",
        "Correct Answer":"Cerebellum"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which of the following is the level of spinal injury with least spasticity?",
        "Option 1":"T10-T9",
        "Option 2":"T11-T10",
        "Option 3":"T11-T12",
        "Option 4":"T12-L1",
        "Option 5":"L2-L3",
        "Correct Answer":"L2-L3"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** Which of the following is most likely to cause brisk reflexes?",
        "Option 1":"L1-2",
        "Option 2":"T12-L1",
        "Option 3":"L2-3",
        "Option 4":"L3-4",
        "Option 5":"L5-S2",
        "Correct Answer":"T12-L1"
    },
    {
        "Question":"34 year old patient after RTA came to emergency room and diagnosed as cauda equina syndrome. What will not present in this syndrome?",
        "Option 1":"Urine retention",
        "Option 2":"Knee hyperreflexia",
        "Option 3":"Overflow incontinence",
        "Option 4":"Saddle anaesthesia",
        "Option 5":"Weakness of both lower limbs",
        "Correct Answer":"Knee hyperreflexia"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 22 year old man has cervical vertebra trauma. He has upper limbs weakness more than the lower limbs. What is the mostly diagnosis?",
        "Option 1":"Tabes dorsalis",
        "Option 2":"Subacute degeneration of the cord",
        "Option 3":"Brown sequerd syndrome",
        "Option 4":"Central cord syndrome",
        "Option 5":"Herpes zoster",
        "Correct Answer":"Central cord syndrome"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** After tapping the knee tendon with medical hammer, the response is quadriceps contraction with knee extension. This reflex carried out by which of the following?",
        "Option 1":"Golgi tendon",
        "Option 2":"Muscle spindle",
        "Option 3":"Brain stem",
        "Option 4":"Cerebral cortex",
        "Option 5":"Cerebellum",
        "Correct Answer":"Muscle spindle"
    },
    {
        "Question":"23 year old male after road traffic accident has C5 fracture then loss all spinal reflexes, what is the first spinal reflex appears after spinal shock?",
        "Option 1":"Delayed planter reflex",
        "Option 2":"Biceps reflex",
        "Option 3":"Triceps reflex",
        "Option 4":"Ankle reflex",
        "Option 5":"Knee reflex",
        "Correct Answer":"Delayed planter reflex"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** Patient suffered from abdominal tumor and after surgery including retroperitoneal node clearance, the patient can\u2019t ejaculate. What is the injured nerve during surgery?",
        "Option 1":"Pelvic splanchnic nerve",
        "Option 2":"Lumber splanchnic nerve",
        "Option 3":"Thoracic splanchnic nerve",
        "Option 4":"Pudendal nerve",
        "Option 5":"Ilioinguinal nerve",
        "Correct Answer":"Lumber splanchnic nerve"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** Young patient after RTA presented by complete loss of sensation and weakness below the level of umbilicus and urine incontinence. Which of the following is might not present after 24 hours?",
        "Option 1":"Loss of bilateral planter reflex",
        "Option 2":"Loss of bilateral ankle reflex",
        "Option 3":"Loss of bulbocavernous reflex",
        "Option 4":"Urine retention",
        "Option 5":"Anal tone",
        "Correct Answer":"Loss of bulbocavernous reflex"
    },
    {
        "Question":"23 years female after RTA presented by saddle anesthesia, back pain, urinary incontinence and weakness in both lower limbs and suspected having cauda equina, what is the appropriate next step?",
        "Option 1":"CT spine",
        "Option 2":"MRI spine",
        "Option 3":"Admit 24 hours in hospital",
        "Option 4":"Give analgesia and examine again",
        "Option 5":"Observation",
        "Correct Answer":"MRI spine"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 34 years old man took a maximal inspiration before exhaling maximally. This is measured  by spirometer. What does this represent?",
        "Option 1":"Vital capacity",
        "Option 2":"Functional residual capacity",
        "Option 3":"Total lung capacity",
        "Option 4":"Inspiratory reserve volume",
        "Option 5":"Residual volume",
        "Correct Answer":"Vital capacity"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** In pre-anesthetic clinic, spirometer is advised to patient to assess his pulmonary function. What is correct regarding lung volumes and capacities?",
        "Option 1":"Vital capacity is sum of inspiratory reserve volume, tidal volume and expiratory reserve volume",
        "Option 2":"Total lung capacity is sum of inspiratory reserve volume and vital capacity",
        "Option 3":"Functional residual volume is sum of inspiratory reserve volume and residual volume",
        "Option 4":"Expiratory reserve volume is volume of air can be expired after normal inspiration",
        "Option 5":"Total lung capacity is vital capacity minus residual volume",
        "Correct Answer":"Vital capacity is sum of inspiratory reserve volume, tidal volume and expiratory reserve volume"
    },
    {
        "Question":"The pleural space is negative with respect to atmospheric pressure except for which of the following?",
        "Option 1":"During a vulsalva maneuver",
        "Option 2":"During muller maneuver",
        "Option 3":"During expiration",
        "Option 4":"During inspiration",
        "Option 5":"During forced inspiration",
        "Correct Answer":"During a vulsalva maneuver"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 45 years old man assessed for routine surgery. His past medical history include COPD and he smoked 40 cigarettes a day for past 30 years. Physical examination shows barrel shaped chest and symmetrical lung expansion and by examination, chest reveals bilateral mild wheezes, what is the most likely spirometer result?",
        "Option 1":"Increased residual volume",
        "Option 2":"Decreased residual volume",
        "Option 3":"Increased FEV1 and FVC",
        "Option 4":"Increase tidal volume",
        "Option 5":"Decreased tidal volume",
        "Correct Answer":"Increased residual volume"
    },
    {
        "Question":"What is the definition of maximum inspiration to maximum expiration in one minute on spirometer?",
        "Option 1":"Maximum voluntary ventilation",
        "Option 2":"Vital capacity",
        "Option 3":"Residual volume",
        "Option 4":"Total lung capacity",
        "Option 5":"None of the above",
        "Correct Answer":"Maximum voluntary ventilation"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** 70 year old man attended a respiratory clinic due to complaint of long standing breathlessness. His spirometer revealed an FEV1 of 1.8 L and FVC of 2.1 L. which of the following is most likely cause?",
        "Option 1":"Alveolitis",
        "Option 2":"Asthma",
        "Option 3":"Bronchiectasis",
        "Option 4":"COPD",
        "Option 5":"Fibrosis",
        "Correct Answer":"Fibrosis"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A young girl is admitted due to attack of dyspnea and shortness of breath. His pulmonary function test show: FEV1 = 1.2 and FVC = 3.6 then some treatment is given, what is mostly diagnosis?",
        "Option 1":"Asthma",
        "Option 2":"Fibrosing alveolitis",
        "Option 3":"Lung collapse",
        "Option 4":"Fibrosis",
        "Option 5":"Asbestosis",
        "Correct Answer":"Asthma"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Male chronic smoker admitted for elective hernioplasty. He has history of dysnea upon ambulating 20-30 meters. His investigations show: PO2 = 7, PCO2 = 4, FEV1 = 500ml and FEV1\/FVC = 90%. What is mostly diagnosis?",
        "Option 1":"Left ventricle failure",
        "Option 2":"Bronchiectasis",
        "Option 3":"Asthma",
        "Option 4":"COPD",
        "Option 5":"Severe restrictive lung disorder",
        "Correct Answer":"Severe restrictive lung disorder"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A woman is in the recovery room receives 15 L oxygen by mask. Blood gas shows Ph = 7.3, PO2 = 11, pCO2 = 7: which receptor is most likely to be stimulated by this blood gas picture?",
        "Option 1":"Adrenergic receptors",
        "Option 2":"Baroreceptors",
        "Option 3":"Chemoreceptors",
        "Option 4":"J receptors",
        "Option 5":"Lung stretch receptors",
        "Correct Answer":"Chemoreceptors"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which single respiratory test parameter is the best prediction for morbidity and mortality after thoracic surgery?",
        "Option 1":"Confronted Flow volume loop",
        "Option 2":"FEV1< 1L",
        "Option 3":"FEV1\/ FVC < 70%",
        "Option 4":"Maximum inspiratory volume < 2 L",
        "Option 5":"Reduced residual volume",
        "Correct Answer":"FEV1< 1L"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 50 year old male smoker with severe COPD presented in ER with dyspnea. Patient after receiving high flow oxygen became drowsy. What is mostly the cause?",
        "Option 1":"Acute respiratory failure",
        "Option 2":"Respiratory alkalosis",
        "Option 3":"Metabolic acidosis",
        "Option 4":"Metabolic alkalosis",
        "Option 5":"Chronic respiratory failure",
        "Correct Answer":"Acute respiratory failure"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 78 year old woman, with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, becomes confused after a right hemicolectomy, she is on 30% Oxygen and her blood gas analysis shows: PO2 = 6.2, PCO2 = 8.5, from what is she most likely to be suffering?",
        "Option 1":"Severe asthma attack",
        "Option 2":"Atelectasis",
        "Option 3":"Pulmonary embolus",
        "Option 4":"Type 1 Respiratory failure",
        "Option 5":"Type 2 Respiratory failure",
        "Correct Answer":"Type 2 Respiratory failure"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which of the following methods is not reliable to measure oxygen on low tissue perfusion?",
        "Option 1":"Swan ganz catheter",
        "Option 2":"Pulmonary capillary catheter",
        "Option 3":"Pulse oximeter",
        "Option 4":"ABG",
        "Option 5":"None of the above",
        "Correct Answer":"Pulse oximeter"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which of the following is indication for assisted for assisted ventilation?",
        "Option 1":"Respiratory rate > 35",
        "Option 2":"pH = 7.2",
        "Option 3":"Sweating",
        "Option 4":"Confusion",
        "Option 5":"PCO2 = 5.7",
        "Correct Answer":"Respiratory rate > 35"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** 25 years old athlete man and his height is about 180 cm, which of the following is correct in a sports physiology lab?",
        "Option 1":"Vital capacity 2 L",
        "Option 2":"Peak expiratory flow in 1 minute is 500 ml",
        "Option 3":"Forced vital capacity is 4 times than in 1st second",
        "Option 4":"FRC 3.5 Liter",
        "Option 5":"Resting respiratory rate 10",
        "Correct Answer":"Peak expiratory flow in 1 minute is 500 ml"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** A 13 year old girl present with severe dyspnea and respiratory distress. She has long history of bronchial asthma. After deterioration of the case (saturation \u2013 CO2), what is the best measure used in critical asthma patient?",
        "Option 1":"CMV",
        "Option 2":"CPAP",
        "Option 3":"Intubation",
        "Option 4":"Steroid",
        "Option 5":"Antibiotic",
        "Correct Answer":"Intubation"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Female patient obese BMI 41, prepared for sleeve gastrectomy, what is the cause of hypoxia in postoperative period?",
        "Option 1":"Increase FRC",
        "Option 2":"Increase VC",
        "Option 3":"Increase ERV",
        "Option 4":"Increase FVC",
        "Option 5":"Decrease IRV",
        "Correct Answer":"Decrease IRV"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** Chemoreceptors in carotid bodies are stimulated mainly by which of the following?",
        "Option 1":"Decrease hydrogen",
        "Option 2":"Increase pH",
        "Option 3":"Decrease pO2",
        "Option 4":"Increase pCO2",
        "Option 5":"Decrease pCO2",
        "Correct Answer":"Decrease pO2"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 20 year old man with a severe head injury is being ventilated using positive pressure or IPPV. Which of the following is a physiological consequence of this?",
        "Option 1":"Increase stroke volume",
        "Option 2":"Reduced venous return",
        "Option 3":"Increase after load",
        "Option 4":"Increase cardiac contractility",
        "Option 5":"Increase atrial filling",
        "Correct Answer":"Reduced venous return"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 60 year old man with a history of angina undergoes an uncomplicated operation, for an inguinal hernia. Postoperatively he is found to be hypotensive, tachycardia and has raised jugular venous pressure. What is the most likely underlying cause of his hypotension?",
        "Option 1":"Reduced afterload",
        "Option 2":"Reduced parasympathetic",
        "Option 3":"Reduced preload",
        "Option 4":"Reduced stroke volume",
        "Option 5":"Reduced sympathetic tone",
        "Correct Answer":"Reduced stroke volume"
    },
    {
        "Question":"57 year old heart transplant recipient is keen to join cardiac rehabilitation program. Which of the following factor is most likely increase cardiac output in this patient with moderate exercise?",
        "Option 1":"Decrease negative intrathoracic pressure",
        "Option 2":"Decrease venous return",
        "Option 3":"Decrease ventricular compliance",
        "Option 4":"Increase atrial filling",
        "Option 5":"Increased intra pericardial pressure",
        "Correct Answer":"Increase atrial filling"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 20 year old man with a severe head injury is being ventilated using positive pressure or IPPV. Which of the following is a physiological consequence of this?",
        "Option 1":"Decreased extracellular fluid volume",
        "Option 2":"Decreased cardiac preload",
        "Option 3":"Increase in intrathoracic blood volume",
        "Option 4":"Increased cardiac preload",
        "Option 5":"Increased cardiac stroke volume",
        "Correct Answer":"Decreased cardiac preload"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** A healthy man in his 20s just after giving general anaesthesia, his BP dropped. What will be the cause of this hypotension?",
        "Option 1":"Reduced stroke volume",
        "Option 2":"Reduced preload",
        "Option 3":"Reduced afterload",
        "Option 4":"Increased SVR",
        "Option 5":"Increased preload",
        "Correct Answer":"Reduced preload"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 30 year old man is stabbed in the left fifth intercostal space. He has a tachycardia but normal blood pressure. The chest Xray is normal. What is the next step?",
        "Option 1":"Arrange an echocardiogram",
        "Option 2":"Arrange emergency thoracotomy in the operating room",
        "Option 3":"Carry out an ECG",
        "Option 4":"Insert a chest drain on the side of the injury with the addition of high pressure suction",
        "Option 5":"Request a CT scan",
        "Correct Answer":"Arrange an echocardiogram"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 25 year old man is admitted having been stabbed in the interior chest. On examination, he is alert and coherent. He has congested neck veins. His pulse is 140 beat\/minute and his blood pressure 90\/60 mmHg. He has normal breath sounds. What is the most likely cause of his cardiac arrest 15 minutes later?",
        "Option 1":"Cardiac tamponade",
        "Option 2":"Congestive cardiac failure",
        "Option 3":"Hypovolemia",
        "Option 4":"Tension pneumothorax",
        "Option 5":"Ventricular arrhythmia",
        "Correct Answer":"Cardiac tamponade"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Healthy 81 year old man develops recurrent syncope and cough with frothy sputum. His general examination shows normal blood pressure and absence of peripheral edema. Auscultation of the chest reveals an ejection systolic murmur chest Xray reveals left ventricular enlargement and pulmonary edema. What is the most likely cause?",
        "Option 1":"Aortic aneurysm",
        "Option 2":"Calcific aortic stenosis",
        "Option 3":"Mitral stenosis",
        "Option 4":"Pulmonary hypertension",
        "Option 5":"Rheumatic heart disease",
        "Correct Answer":"Calcific aortic stenosis"
    },
    {
        "Question":"35 year old man has ejection systolic murmur on auscultation with symptom of pulmonary edema. What is the valve problem?",
        "Option 1":"Aortic regurge",
        "Option 2":"Aortic stenosis",
        "Option 3":"Mitral regurge",
        "Option 4":"Mitral stenosis",
        "Option 5":"Tricuspid regurge",
        "Correct Answer":"Aortic stenosis"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Closure of the tricuspid valve occurs at the onset of which phase of the cardiac cycle?",
        "Option 1":"Isovolumic relaxation",
        "Option 2":"Rapid and reduced filling",
        "Option 3":"Protodiastolic phase",
        "Option 4":"Rapid and reduced ejection",
        "Option 5":"Isovolumic contraction",
        "Correct Answer":"Isovolumic contraction"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which of the following is important conduction system of the heart?",
        "Option 1":"SA node",
        "Option 2":"AV node",
        "Option 3":"Trabecula carinae",
        "Option 4":"Chorda tendani",
        "Option 5":"None of the above",
        "Correct Answer":"AV node"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** Sinoatrial node nerve supply comes form",
        "Option 1":"Fibers from vagus nerve",
        "Option 2":"Sympathetic fibers",
        "Option 3":"Fibers form cardiac plexus",
        "Option 4":"Somatic fibers",
        "Option 5":"Fibers from glossopharyngeal",
        "Correct Answer":"Fibers form cardiac plexus"
    },
    {
        "Question":"In describing the SA node, which of the following statements is correct?",
        "Option 1":"It is part of the somatic nervous system",
        "Option 2":"It is usually supplied by the left coronary artery",
        "Option 3":"It lies in the wall of the left atrium",
        "Option 4":"It lies in the wall of the right ventricle",
        "Option 5":"It receives fibers derived from the vagus nerves",
        "Correct Answer":"It receives fibers derived from the vagus nerves"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which is false about the SA node anatomy and physiology?",
        "Option 1":"Pacemaker of the heart",
        "Option 2":"Present in the wall of right atrium beside SVC",
        "Option 3":"Has somatic nerve supply",
        "Option 4":"Has vagal nerve supply",
        "Option 5":"Has sympathetic nerve supply",
        "Correct Answer":"Has somatic nerve supply"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 53 year old man complains of crushing chest pain at rest. He has chronic hypertension and is a heavy smoker. His pulse is 138 and BP 140\/90 mmHg. What is the principal causes underlying his reduced coronary artery blood flow?",
        "Option 1":"Decreased cardiac muscle tension",
        "Option 2":"Decreased coronary oxygen extraction",
        "Option 3":"Decreased diastolic interval",
        "Option 4":"Decreased systolic interval",
        "Option 5":"Decreased vagal tone",
        "Correct Answer":"Decreased diastolic interval"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which of the following statements is true with relation to cardiac muscle?",
        "Option 1":"Contraction does not involve release of Ca by the sarcoplasmic reticulum",
        "Option 2":"Contraction is triggered by an influx of Ca through the sarcolemma",
        "Option 3":"Excitation is passed from one cardiac cell to another through desmosomes",
        "Option 4":"Hypertrophy is brought about by division of existing cardiac cells",
        "Option 5":"There is capacity for regeneration",
        "Correct Answer":"Contraction is triggered by an influx of Ca through the sarcolemma"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 25 year old male athlete is in training. At rest, how many liters of blood per minute does his heart pump out?",
        "Option 1":"2 to 3",
        "Option 2":"5 to 6",
        "Option 3":"7 to 8",
        "Option 4":"8 to 9",
        "Option 5":"15 to 20",
        "Correct Answer":"5 to 6"
    },
    {
        "Question":"What is amount of blood in stroke volume in normal heart at rest?",
        "Option 1":"50 ml\/beat",
        "Option 2":"60 ml\/beat",
        "Option 3":"70 ml\/beat",
        "Option 4":"90 ml\/beat",
        "Option 5":"110 ml\/beat",
        "Correct Answer":"70 ml\/beat"
    },
    {
        "Question":"What is the amount pumped in aorta per cardiac cycle?",
        "Option 1":"70 ml",
        "Option 2":"95 ml",
        "Option 3":"5 litres",
        "Option 4":"2 litres",
        "Option 5":"13 litres",
        "Correct Answer":"70 ml"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Ventricular repolarization in ECG represented by which wave in ECG?",
        "Option 1":"P wave",
        "Option 2":"QRS wave",
        "Option 3":"T wave",
        "Option 4":"ST segment",
        "Option 5":"None of the above",
        "Correct Answer":"T wave"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which part of the ECG represents atrial depolarization?",
        "Option 1":"P wave",
        "Option 2":"QRS wave",
        "Option 3":"T wave",
        "Option 4":"ST segment",
        "Option 5":"None of the above",
        "Correct Answer":"P wave"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Patient with atrial fibrillation. Which wave of these jugular waves will be absent?",
        "Option 1":"A wave",
        "Option 2":"X wave",
        "Option 3":"C wave",
        "Option 4":"V wave",
        "Option 5":"Y wave",
        "Correct Answer":"A wave"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 26 year old man motorcyclist loses 1 L of blood secondary to an open fracture of the femur sustained in RTA. Which of the following is the most likely earliest compensatory response in hypovolemia in this patient?",
        "Option 1":"Baroreceptors induced venoconstriction",
        "Option 2":"Capillary fluid shifts",
        "Option 3":"Decreased atrial natruritic peptide secretion",
        "Option 4":"Renal fluid retention",
        "Option 5":"Renin angiotensin system activation",
        "Correct Answer":"Baroreceptors induced venoconstriction"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** 30 years old man admitted due to absent pulse in his right upper limb. By cardiological examination, there is atrial fibrillation. What is the expected disease association with?",
        "Option 1":"Left ventricular thrombus",
        "Option 2":"Atherosclerosis",
        "Option 3":"Small vessel vasculitis",
        "Option 4":"Left atrial myxoma",
        "Option 5":"Paradoxical embolus",
        "Correct Answer":"Left atrial myxoma"
    },
    {
        "Question":"What is the cerebral perfusion pressure calculation if blood pressure is 110\/80 and intra cranial pressure is 18?",
        "Option 1":"72",
        "Option 2":"82",
        "Option 3":"92",
        "Option 4":"102",
        "Option 5":"112",
        "Correct Answer":"72"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** A young patient has brain trauma due to car accident. Increased intra cranial tension was observed, which of the following methods has been used to lower ICP?",
        "Option 1":"Increase PCO2",
        "Option 2":"Decrease PCO2",
        "Option 3":"Increase PO2",
        "Option 4":"Decrease PO2",
        "Option 5":"None of the above",
        "Correct Answer":"Decrease PCO2"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 19 year old man is attacked outside a club and beaten with a baseball bat. He sustained a blow to the right side of his head. He is brought to the emergency room and a policy of observation is adopted. His GCS deteriorated and he becomes comatose. Which of the following parameters is likely to be present?",
        "Option 1":"Hypertension and bradycardia",
        "Option 2":"Hypotension and tachycardia",
        "Option 3":"Hypertension and tachycardia",
        "Option 4":"Hypertension and bradycardia",
        "Option 5":"Normotension and bradycardia",
        "Correct Answer":"Hypertension and bradycardia"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 19 year old man is attacked outside a club and beaten with a baseball bat. He sustained a blow to the right side of his head. He is brought to the emergency room and a policy of observation is adopted. His GCS deteriorated and he becomes comatose. What is the least likely measure to decrease the intracranial tension?",
        "Option 1":"Head tilt up 15-30 degrees",
        "Option 2":"Hypothermia",
        "Option 3":"Analgesia and sedation",
        "Option 4":"3% saline",
        "Option 5":"Mild hypocapnia",
        "Correct Answer":"Hypothermia"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** A 40 year old man is brought to the emergency department with head injury due to brain hemorrhage and increased ICP. Which mechanism first occurs due to raised intracranial tension?",
        "Option 1":"Bradycardia",
        "Option 2":"Hypertension",
        "Option 3":"Decreased mental state",
        "Option 4":"Pupil dilatation",
        "Option 5":"Irregular respiration",
        "Correct Answer":"Decreased mental state"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 30 year old is admitted to the ICU with isolated severe head injury. A CT scan shows multiple intra-cerebral bleeds but no midline shift. He is intubated and ventilated. His pupils are dilated and react sluggishly to light. His heart rate is 50 and BP is 170\/110 and his respiratory rate is 10 breath \/ min. the rising blood pressure is likely to be caused by which of the following?",
        "Option 1":"Aortic and carotid baroreceptor stimulation",
        "Option 2":"Cortisol stimulation",
        "Option 3":"Renin angiotensin stimulation",
        "Option 4":"Sympathetic stimulation related to blood loss",
        "Option 5":"Sympathetic stimulation related to intracranial pressure",
        "Correct Answer":"Sympathetic stimulation related to intracranial pressure"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 64 year old woman sustained a closed head injury. She is sedated and ventilated in the emergency room. A CT scan of the brain shows significant cerebral edema. Her intracranial pressure is elevated. Which of the following therapeutic strategies is most likely to lead to a rapid transient reduction in her intracranial pressure?",
        "Option 1":"Elevation of central venous pressure",
        "Option 2":"Elevation of PO2",
        "Option 3":"Elevation of systolic arterial pressure",
        "Option 4":"Reduction in cerebral perfusion pressure",
        "Option 5":"Reduction of PCO2",
        "Correct Answer":"Reduction of PCO2"
    },
    {
        "Question":"What is the percentage of blood flow to brain from cardiac output?",
        "Option 1":"5%",
        "Option 2":"10%",
        "Option 3":"15%",
        "Option 4":"20%",
        "Option 5":"25%",
        "Correct Answer":"15%"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** A 25 year old man sustained a right side head injury and presents to the emergency department with GCS 3. He has dilated pupil on the side of injury and is hypertensive and bradycardia. His respiratory rate is slow and irregular and SPO2 = 95%. Which of the following reason for bradycardia?",
        "Option 1":"Decrease in activity of cardiopulmonary receptors",
        "Option 2":"Decrease in activity of baroreceptors in carotid sinus",
        "Option 3":"Decrease in activity of chemoreceptors in aortic body",
        "Option 4":"Increase in activity of baroreceptors in aortic sinus",
        "Option 5":"Increase in activity of chemoreceptors in carotid body",
        "Correct Answer":"Increase in activity of baroreceptors in aortic sinus"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 26 year old man is admitted to the emergency department with multiple peripheral fractures. He is clinically shocked. Which is the structure responsible for the first hemostatic response to a fall in systemic arterial blood pressure?",
        "Option 1":"Adenohypophysis",
        "Option 2":"Baroreceptors",
        "Option 3":"Chemoreceptors",
        "Option 4":"Renin",
        "Option 5":"Neurohypophysis",
        "Correct Answer":"Baroreceptors"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 24 year old man is brought to emergency department following RTA. The primary survey detects grade 3 shock as a result of pelvic fracture. Which of the following pathophysiological mechanisms is the first to be activated to maintain circulatory blood pressure?",
        "Option 1":"Antidiuretic hormone",
        "Option 2":"Atrial natruritic peptide",
        "Option 3":"Parasympathetic nervous system",
        "Option 4":"Renin angiotensin system",
        "Option 5":"Sympathetic nervous system",
        "Correct Answer":"Sympathetic nervous system"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Female patient with chest trauma and after 9 days came to hospital shocked. Heart rate = 120, blood pressure = 90\/60, with raised JVP, what is your diagnosis?",
        "Option 1":"Hypovolemic shock",
        "Option 2":"Neurogenic shock",
        "Option 3":"Hemopericardium",
        "Option 4":"Septic shock",
        "Option 5":"Anaphylactic shock",
        "Correct Answer":"Hemopericardium"
    },
    {
        "Question":"30 year old patient with chest trauma. He has bruises on the chest and external jugular veins are visible. What is the type of shock occur?",
        "Option 1":"Distributive",
        "Option 2":"Obstructive",
        "Option 3":"Hypovolemic",
        "Option 4":"Neurogenic",
        "Option 5":"Vagal",
        "Correct Answer":"Obstructive"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A man has major surgery 7 days ago, presented to emergency with hypotension and pulse rate 120 and warm peripheries, what is the condition of this patient?",
        "Option 1":"Neurogenic shock",
        "Option 2":"Anaphylactic shock",
        "Option 3":"Septic shock",
        "Option 4":"Hypovolemic shock",
        "Option 5":"Cardiogenic shock",
        "Correct Answer":"Septic shock"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 21 year old man is undergoing an inguinal hernia repair and receives a dose of intravenous co-amoxiclav. He is reported to have a penicillin allergy. Over the next few minutes his vitals are: pulse: 130 bpm, blood pressure: 60\/40. What is the first line of treatment?",
        "Option 1":"Hydrocortisone 100 mg IV",
        "Option 2":"Adrenaline 1:1000 IV",
        "Option 3":"Chlorpheniramine 10 mg IV",
        "Option 4":"Adrenaline 1:1000 IM",
        "Option 5":"Adrenaline 1:10000 IV",
        "Correct Answer":"Adrenaline 1:1000 IM"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A male patient admitted in ICU after rupture aortic aneurysm. Heart rate 100, blood pressure 90\/60, Hb = 9, cardiac index = 1.9(normal <2.5), pulmonary wedge pressure = 19 (normal <15), stroke volume = 40 (normal = 60-90), which of the following describes these options?",
        "Option 1":"Administer 250 ml of gelufusin",
        "Option 2":"Administer 1 unit of RBCS",
        "Option 3":"Commence epinephrine",
        "Option 4":"Commence norepinephrine",
        "Option 5":"Commence vasopressin",
        "Correct Answer":"Commence epinephrine"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A fit 30 year old male denotes 500 ml of blood. Which of the processes outlined below is below is most likely to occur?",
        "Option 1":"Reduction of urine output",
        "Option 2":"Activation of the renin angiotensin system",
        "Option 3":"Sweating",
        "Option 4":"Fall in mean arterial pressure",
        "Option 5":"Tachypnea",
        "Correct Answer":"Activation of the renin angiotensin system"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 50 year old patient presented to emergency room with high systemic vascular resistance, low cardiac output and low central venous pressure, what is mostly the type of shock?",
        "Option 1":"Septic shock",
        "Option 2":"Neurogenic shock",
        "Option 3":"Cardiogenic shock",
        "Option 4":"Hemorrhagic shock",
        "Option 5":"Anaphylactic shock",
        "Correct Answer":"Hemorrhagic shock"
    },
    {
        "Question":"50 year old patient presented to emergency room with high systemic vascular resistance, low  cardiac output and high central venous pressure, what is the type of shock?",
        "Option 1":"Septic shock",
        "Option 2":"Neurogenic shock",
        "Option 3":"Cardiogenic shock",
        "Option 4":"Hemorrhagic shock",
        "Option 5":"Anaphylactic shock",
        "Correct Answer":"Cardiogenic shock"
    },
    {
        "Question":"50 year old patient after colectomy operation admitted with HDU, his urine output chart is monitored hourly as 80 ml then 80 ml then 0 ml then 0 ml in last 5 hours, what is the cause of decrease in his urine output posoperatively?",
        "Option 1":"Blocked catheter",
        "Option 2":"Hypovolemia",
        "Option 3":"Neurogenic shock",
        "Option 4":"Anaphylactic shock",
        "Option 5":"Septic shock",
        "Correct Answer":"Blocked catheter"
    },
    {
        "Question":"The first line of treatment of anaphylactic shock is IM adrenaline, adrenaline increase heart rate by acting on which receptor?",
        "Option 1":"A1 receptors",
        "Option 2":"A2 receptors",
        "Option 3":"B1 receptors",
        "Option 4":"B2 receptors",
        "Option 5":"D receptors",
        "Correct Answer":"B1 receptors"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Septic shock mainly treated by noradrenaline, which receptor does noradrenaline mainly bind to ?",
        "Option 1":"A1 receptors",
        "Option 2":"A2 receptors",
        "Option 3":"B1 receptors",
        "Option 4":"B2 receptors",
        "Option 5":"D receptors",
        "Correct Answer":"A1 receptors"
    },
    {
        "Question":"25 years old patient with bee sting shock presented with heart rate 120, blood pressure 60\/40, what is the first line of treatment for this type of shock?",
        "Option 1":"IM adrenaline",
        "Option 2":"IV antihistamine",
        "Option 3":"IV fluid",
        "Option 4":"IV steroid",
        "Option 5":"IV antihistaminic",
        "Correct Answer":"IM adrenaline"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Isoprenaline has an inotropic effect through acting on which receptors?",
        "Option 1":"A1 receptors",
        "Option 2":"A2 receptors",
        "Option 3":"B1 receptors",
        "Option 4":"B2 receptors",
        "Option 5":"D receptors",
        "Correct Answer":"B1 receptors"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Beta 1 blocker found mainly in which organ of the following?",
        "Option 1":"Blood vessel",
        "Option 2":"Ventricle",
        "Option 3":"Bronchi",
        "Option 4":"GIT",
        "Option 5":"Lung",
        "Correct Answer":"Ventricle"
    },
    {
        "Question":"A 34 year old patient was in operation with tourniquet. After release of tourniquet, what is the substance released causing vasodilatation ?",
        "Option 1":"Noradrenaline",
        "Option 2":"Vasopressin",
        "Option 3":"Histamine",
        "Option 4":"Serotonin",
        "Option 5":"Adrenaline",
        "Correct Answer":"Histamine"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** Which of the following substance cause vasodilatation?",
        "Option 1":"Interlukin 1",
        "Option 2":"Bradykinin",
        "Option 3":"Complement 3a",
        "Option 4":"Platelet activating factor",
        "Option 5":"Thromboxane A2",
        "Correct Answer":"Bradykinin"
    },
    {
        "Question":"20 year old patient with history of sickle cell anemia and presented now with painful priapism, aspiration was done and failed to correct it and now one of these drugs is injected, which drug can be used?",
        "Option 1":"Alprostadil",
        "Option 2":"Salbutamol",
        "Option 3":"Phenylephrine",
        "Option 4":"Atenolol",
        "Option 5":"All of the above",
        "Correct Answer":"Phenylephrine"
    },
    {
        "Question":"All of the following substances are vasodilating substances except which one?",
        "Option 1":"Serotonin",
        "Option 2":"Histamine",
        "Option 3":"Prostacyclin",
        "Option 4":"Nitric oxide",
        "Option 5":"Bradykinin",
        "Correct Answer":"Serotonin"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which is the precursor of isoprenaline that stimulates B1 receptors on the heart in low dose and stimulates the alpha 1 receptors at high doses?",
        "Option 1":"Dopamine",
        "Option 2":"Dobutamine",
        "Option 3":"Noradrenaline",
        "Option 4":"Adrenaline",
        "Option 5":"Serotonin",
        "Correct Answer":"Dopamine"
    },
    {
        "Question":"What is the inotrope agent with mixed vasodilatation and vasoconstriction properties?",
        "Option 1":"Dobutamine",
        "Option 2":"Noradrenaline",
        "Option 3":"Adrenaline",
        "Option 4":"Milrinone",
        "Option 5":"Dopamine",
        "Correct Answer":"Dopamine"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which of the following inotropes causes phosphodiesterase inhibitor to increase CAMP and so increases contractility?",
        "Option 1":"Dobutamine",
        "Option 2":"Noradrenaline",
        "Option 3":"Adrenaline",
        "Option 4":"Milrinone",
        "Option 5":"Dopamine",
        "Correct Answer":"Milrinone"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Protein C is used mainly in which type of shock as treatment>",
        "Option 1":"Hypovolemic",
        "Option 2":"Neurogenic",
        "Option 3":"Anaphylactic",
        "Option 4":"Septic",
        "Option 5":"Cardiogenic",
        "Correct Answer":"Septic"
    },
    {
        "Question":"All are signs of SIRS except:",
        "Option 1":"Pulse more than 90",
        "Option 2":"Respiratory rete more than 20",
        "Option 3":"Blood pressure less than 100\/60",
        "Option 4":"TLC more than 12 or less than 4",
        "Option 5":"Temperature more than 38 or less than 36",
        "Correct Answer":"Blood pressure less than 100\/60"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** According to starling law in capillaries, what is filtration pressure if hydrostatic pressure of capillaries is 45, hydrostatic pressure of bowman is 10, oncotic pressure in capillaries is 27 and oncotic pressure in bowman is 0 , what is filtration pressure?",
        "Option 1":"55",
        "Option 2":"60",
        "Option 3":"8",
        "Option 4":"25",
        "Option 5":"18",
        "Correct Answer":"8"
    },
    {
        "Question":"ST elevation in lead II, III, aVF in ECG , which type of ischemia is present?",
        "Option 1":"Inferior MI",
        "Option 2":"Anterior MI",
        "Option 3":"Septal MI",
        "Option 4":"Lateral MI",
        "Option 5":"Anteroseptal MI",
        "Correct Answer":"Inferior MI"
    },
    {
        "Question":"40 year old has tricuspid stenosis, in which wave of jugular venous pressure do we see the physical findings?",
        "Option 1":"V",
        "Option 2":"Y",
        "Option 3":"A",
        "Option 4":"X",
        "Option 5":"P",
        "Correct Answer":"A"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** 23 year old man after RTA came to ER with blood pressure 70\/30, heart rate 145, respiratory rate 30, this patient in which class of hypovolemic shock?",
        "Option 1":"Class 1",
        "Option 2":"Class 2",
        "Option 3":"Class 3",
        "Option 4":"Class 4",
        "Option 5":"Class 5",
        "Correct Answer":"Class 4"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** 50 year old man suffered form sepsis in ICU, qSOFA score used to assess his condition, qSOFA score includes which of the following?",
        "Option 1":"Respiratory rate < 20",
        "Option 2":"Systolic blood pressure < 90",
        "Option 3":"Altered mental status",
        "Option 4":"Temperature < 36",
        "Option 5":"None of the above",
        "Correct Answer":"Systolic blood pressure < 90"
    },
    {
        "Question":"30 years old man after car accident and blunt chest trauma presented by hypotension, raised jugular venous pressure with muffled heart sound and then he arrested after 15 minutes, what is the cause of this arrest?",
        "Option 1":"Reduced LV contractility",
        "Option 2":"Reduced LV diastole",
        "Option 3":"Reduced RV contractility",
        "Option 4":"Reduced RV diastole",
        "Option 5":"Reduced blood volume",
        "Correct Answer":"Reduced RV diastole"
    },
    {
        "Question":"50 year old patient with cardiogenic shock due to myocardial ischemia. What to give to him having marked heart contractility and low vascular contractility effect?",
        "Option 1":"Adrenaline",
        "Option 2":"Noradrenaline",
        "Option 3":"Dobutamine",
        "Option 4":"Dopamine",
        "Option 5":"Epinephrine",
        "Correct Answer":"Dobutamine"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** Which receptors of the following does dobutamine act on to reduce blood pressure?",
        "Option 1":"Beta 1",
        "Option 2":"Beta 2",
        "Option 3":"Alpha 1",
        "Option 4":"Alpha 2",
        "Option 5":"Dopamine",
        "Correct Answer":"Beta 2"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** 23 year old patient came to emergency department with hypotension after RTA, first baroreceptor response would be at?",
        "Option 1":"Aortic arch",
        "Option 2":"Carotid sinus",
        "Option 3":"Superior vena cava",
        "Option 4":"External carotid artery",
        "Option 5":"Carotid body",
        "Correct Answer":"Carotid sinus"
    },
    {
        "Question":"How body correct or increase left coronary artery perfusion?",
        "Option 1":"Decrease diastolic blood pressure",
        "Option 2":"Increase systolic blood pressure",
        "Option 3":"End diastolic volume increase",
        "Option 4":"Left ventricular pressure increase",
        "Option 5":"Decrease coronary artery resistance",
        "Correct Answer":"Decrease coronary artery resistance"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which of the following increase contractility as isoprenaline on heart by acting on B1?",
        "Option 1":"Dopamine",
        "Option 2":"Adrenaline",
        "Option 3":"Noradrenaline",
        "Option 4":"Dobutamine",
        "Option 5":"Ephedrine",
        "Correct Answer":"Dobutamine"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which of the following is more risky during operation for patients need surgery?",
        "Option 1":"Aortic regurge",
        "Option 2":"Aortic stenosis",
        "Option 3":"Mitral stenosis",
        "Option 4":"Mitral regurge",
        "Option 5":"Tricuspid stenosis",
        "Correct Answer":"Aortic stenosis"
    },
    {
        "Question":"73 year old man presented by chest pain and diagnosed as angina on going uphill, what is mainly the cause?",
        "Option 1":"Aortic stenosis",
        "Option 2":"Aortic sclerosis",
        "Option 3":"Aortic regurgitation",
        "Option 4":"Mitral stenosis",
        "Option 5":"Tricuspid stenosis",
        "Correct Answer":"Aortic sclerosis"
    },
    {
        "Question":"23 years old patient after doing CT abdomen and pelvis developed respiratory distress, perioral swelling and hypotension, what is the expected diagnosis?",
        "Option 1":"Neurogenic shock",
        "Option 2":"Anaphylactic shock",
        "Option 3":"Septic shock",
        "Option 4":"Hypovolemic shock",
        "Option 5":"Cardiogenic shock",
        "Correct Answer":"Anaphylactic shock"
    },
    {
        "Question":"What is the cerebral perfusion pressure formula?",
        "Option 1":"Intracranial pressure \u2013 mean arterial blood pressure",
        "Option 2":"Intracranial pressure = systolic blood pressure",
        "Option 3":"Mean arterial blood pressure \u2013 intracranial pressure",
        "Option 4":"Systolic blood pressure \u2013 intracranial pressure",
        "Option 5":"Diastolic blood pressure - intracranial pressure",
        "Correct Answer":"Mean arterial blood pressure \u2013 intracranial pressure"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Portion of blood in pulmonary bed or circulation",
        "Option 1":"10 to 15%",
        "Option 2":"20 to 25%",
        "Option 3":"25 \u2013 30 %",
        "Option 4":"50 to 60 %",
        "Option 5":"80 %",
        "Correct Answer":"10 to 15%"
    },
    {
        "Question":"70 year old male patient suffered from dyspnea, orthopnea and on examination suspected pulmonary edema with congested neck veins,  what is the appropriate treatment?",
        "Option 1":"Norepinephrine",
        "Option 2":"Epinephrine",
        "Option 3":"Vasopressin",
        "Option 4":"Dobutamine",
        "Option 5":"Labetalol",
        "Correct Answer":"Dobutamine"
    },
    {
        "Question":"37 year old man after blunt trauma in RTA diagnosed having pneumoperitoneum then 2 hours later, he became shocked, what is the pathophysiology?",
        "Option 1":"Decrease venous return",
        "Option 2":"Increase venous return",
        "Option 3":"Sepsis",
        "Option 4":"Anaphylactic shock",
        "Option 5":"Cardiogenic shock",
        "Correct Answer":"Decrease venous return"
    },
    {
        "Question":"** 50 year old male with history of angina and presented with left colon cancer, and made an operation and on table, there is bowel lavage of left colon, then complained from dyspnea after 2 days. What is the expectant diagnosis?",
        "Option 1":"Broncopnumonia",
        "Option 2":"Lobar pneumonia",
        "Option 3":"Pulmonary embolism",
        "Option 4":"Sepsis",
        "Option 5":"Left ventricular failure",
        "Correct Answer":"Left ventricular failure"
    },
    {
        "Question":"Which of the following has adverse effect on cerebral perfusion?",
        "Option 1":"MABP 95",
        "Option 2":"CO2 = 8.5",
        "Option 3":"Decrease intracranial tension",
        "Option 4":"Hyperventilation",
        "Option 5":"Increase blood pressure",
        "Correct Answer":"CO2 = 8.5"
    },
    {
        "Question":"49 year old made CT and develop perioral swelling and shortness of breathing, what is the appropriate management?",
        "Option 1":"IV fluids",
        "Option 2":"Oxygen supply",
        "Option 3":"IM adrenaline",
        "Option 4":"Blood transfusion",
        "Option 5":"IV adrenaline",
        "Correct Answer":"IM adrenaline"
    }
]